Preliminary Inventory of the Diane Ravitch Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Diane Ravitch papers
1956-2007
2003C61
Hoover Institution Archives
63 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 45 digital files (.002 GB) (28.1 linear feet)
The Diane Ravitch papers consist of speeches and writings, correspondence, printed matter, reports, and studies relating to education in the United States. She is a professor, prolific writer, and an advocate of improvements in American education. Collection includes research materials used by her for writing books
Ravitch, Diane
Access
Collection is open for research. Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2003, with additions through 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Chronology
1938 Born, Houston, Texas
1960 B.A. from Wellesley College, Massachusetts
1974 Author, The Great School Wars, New York City, 1805-1873
1975 Received a Ph.D. in history of American education, Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, Columbia University, New York Received a Delta Kappa Gamma Award for the Great School Wars: New York City, 1805-1973
1978 Author, The Revisionists Revised
1979 Member, National Academy of Education
1980- Trustee, New York Public Library Author, The Troubled Crusade: American Education, 1945-1980 Director, John Dewey Foundation
1984 Member, Society of American Historians
1984-1985 Selected as a Phi Beta Kappa Visiting Scholar
1985 Author, The Schools We Deserve Member, American Academy of Arts and Sciences
1986 Awarded, Henry Allen Moe Prize in Humanities by the American Philosophical Society
1987 Author (with Chester E. Finn, Jr.), What Do Our 17-Year-Olds Know?
1989 Advised Teachers Solidarity and the Ministry of Education in Poland Received the Wellesley College Alumnae Achievement Award
1991 Editor, The American Reader Awarded a medal by the Polish Government for the work on behalf of Solidarity
1991-1993 Assistant Secretary of Education and Counselor to the Secretary of Education Lamar Alexander in the administration of President George H. W. Bush
1992 Edited (with Abigail Thernstrom), The Democracy Reader
1993-1994 Visiting Fellow in Governmental Studies, Brookings Institution Author, National Standards in American Education: A Citizen's Guide
1995-2005 Held the Brown Chair in Education Studies, Brookings Institution
1996 Author (with Chester E. Finn, Jr.), Education Reform, 1995-1996
1997 Author, A Tribute to Al Shanker Author (with Joseph P. Viteritti), New Schools for A New Century: The Redesign of Urban Education
1997-2004 Member, National Assessment Government Board
1998 Received the Horace Kidger Award of the New England History Teachers Association
2000 Author, The American Reader: Words that Moved a Nation, and Left Back: A Century of Battles Over School Reform
2001 Author (with Joseph P. Viteritti), Making good Citizens: Education and Civil Society
2002 Elected, Eleanor Roosevelt Fellow of the American Academy of Political and Social Sciences
2003 Author, The Language Police: How Pressure Groups Restrict What Students Learn Author (with Joseph P. Viteritti), City Schools: Lessons from New York
2004 Author (with Chester E. Finn, Jr.), The Mad Mad World of Textbook Adoption Author, A Consumer Guide to High History Text Books
2005 Author, Brookings Papers on Education Policy Received the John Dewey Award from the United Federation of Teachers of New York City
2006 Author (with Michael Ravitch), The English Reader: What Every Literate Person Needs to Know
2007 Author (with Chester E. Finn. Jr.), Beyond the Basics: Achieving a Liberal Education for All
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Diane Ravitch consist of correspondence, printed matter, reports, research materials, speeches and writings, and studies. They document her contributions to the cause of education in the United States. They reflect her efforts to set up standards for teaching and textbooks and deal with such issues as multiculturalism and bilingual education. They also bring to light the recognition she received outside the United States from European countries such as Poland.
Her papers have been kept in their original order. The audio-visual materials such as audio cassettes, CD Rom, diskettes, photographic prints, and VHS tapes have been arranged alphabetically by date and presented at the end of this guide.
The papers of Diane Ravitch were acquired by Hoover Institution Archives in 2003.
Education--United States.
- Education, 1967-1987 (Box-folder 1: 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes Holt basic reading system, description of Human Kind Project, correspondence, and memoranda relating to various educational issues
- Guidelines for the representation of exceptional persons, selection of text books, and literature selection, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- List of recommended textbooks, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Memoranda, 1974-2006 and undated (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Printed matter, 1972-1987 and undated (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Holt Reading System Report, 1974 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Miscellany, 1988 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Writings - Left Back: A Century of Battles over School System, 2000 (Box-folder 2: 2-13)
  Includes introduction, draft chapters, conclusion, and end notes
- Correspondence (Box 3)
  - undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - 1977 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - 1978 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - 1979-1980 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - 1981-1987 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    Includes a thank you letter, 1985, from William Jefferson Clinton for her "interesting book," Challenges to the Humanities
  - 1988-1989 (Box-folder 3: 7-8)
    Includes a letter from John M. Olin Foundation, 1988
  - 1990 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - 1991 (Box-folder 4: 2-3)
  - 1992 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - 1993-1995 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - 1996-1997 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - 1998-1999 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - 2000-2005 (Box-folder 4: 8)
- Writings - The Language Police: How Pressure Groups Restrict What Students Learn, 2003 (Box-folder 5: 1)
- Records relating to "History Adoption,", 1990 (Box-folder 5: 2)
- Baltic States - Lithuania and Estonia, 1986-1987 and undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
  Case history, letter, and report
- Brookings Institution, 1985-1993 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  Includes invoice, report, and correspondence, as well as a letter confirming Diane Ravitch's appointment as Adjunct Professor of History and Education, Department of Philosophy and the Social Sciences
- Arab community, 1987 and undated (Box-folder 5: 5)
  Includes history and social science programs, and testimony
- American community, 1987 and undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
  Correspondence and printed matter
- Chinese community, 1987 and undated (Box-folder 5: 7)
  Letter and report
- Gays and lesbians, 1987 and undated (Box-folder 5: 8)
  Printed matter and testimony
- Indian community, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  Letter and printed matter
- Jewish community, 1987 and undated (Box-folder 5: 10)
  Correspondence, printed matter, and statement
- Polish community, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 11)
- Right to Die, 1981 and undated (Box-folder 5: 12)
  Printed matter
- Turkish community, 1987 and undated (Box-folder 5: 13)
  Comment on model curriculum for human rights and genocide, memoranda, and printed matter
- Ukrainian community, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  Draft for State Board of Education on Model Curriculum for human rights and genocide, proposal, and Soviet press sources on the Ukrainian Famine of 1932-1933
- Research Materials (photocopies)
  - Correspondence on various topics, 1931-1938 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    including pre-publication critiques of "An Introduction"
  - Reviews of Shackled Diplomacy: The Permanent Factors of Foreign Policies of Nations by Michael Demiashkevich, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Michael Demiashkevich's "Will,", 1933 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    and letter from Anna Demiashkevich after his death, 1938.
  - "Essential Movement,", 1937-1938 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    Includes photocopies of correspondence and tentative theses of the Essentialist Education Association
  - Reviews of "An Introduction,", 1935 and undated (Box-folder 6: 5)
    Includes related correspondence, 1935-1936. Photocopies
  - Russian Student Fund, 1925-1932 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    Correspondence. Photocopies
  - Critique of "An Introduction" probably by Michael Demiashkevich's students, 1935-1936 and undated (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Correspondence relating to health, desire to leave Peabody College, and financial concerns, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    Photocopies of Michael Demiashkevich's personal and professional correspondence
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1937-1938 and undated (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Collected Articles on Education, 1939-2002 and undated (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Collected Articles on Education, 1975-2003 (Box-folder 7: 1)
- Notebooks, 1990 and undated (Box-folder 7: 2)
- Article by Kerri Llewellyn, 1997 (Box-folder 7: 3)
- Printed copy of Diane Ravitch's book, The Language Police: How Pressure Groups Restrict What Students Learn, 2003 (Box-folder 7: 4)
- Education, 1949-1950 and undated (Box-folder 7: 5-6)
  Includes materials relating to issues about curriculum, list of books and schools participating in a survey, notes, printed matter, and reviews of books
- Records of the New Jersey Board of Education, 2003 and undated (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
  Includes photocopy of few pages from the Coming of Age by Bruce Emra, Vol. I
- Alexander, Lamar, 1991 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  Letter
- Ratliff, Ruby G., 1985 (Box-folder 8: 4)
- Knopf, Alfred, 2001 (Box-folder 8: 5)
- Left Back: A Century of Battles over School Reform, 2000 (Box-folder 8: 6-7)
  Includes commentary, correspondence, printed matter, promotional schedule, and television talk show
- The Language Police, 2003 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  Printed copy of the book
- Letter and article by Howard Gardner, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- "An Intellectualism in American Education," Distinguished Lectures, Social Science Research Institute, Northern Illinois University, Illinois, undated (Box-folder 9: 3)
- National Standards and Assessments: A Strategy for Reform of American Education - Project proposal - Governmental Studies, 1993 April (Box-folder 9: 4)
- "A Writer's Life," address, Sixth Annual Authors' Dinner, University of Alabama, 1992 April 7 (Box-folder 9: 5)
- "A Scholar in Washington," The Key Reporter, 1996 Summer (Box-folder 9: 6)
- Notes, 1977 and undated (Box-folder 9: 7)
- Miscellany, 2001 (Box-folder 9: 8)
- Censorship, 1984-1998 (Box-folder 9: 9-12)
  Includes articles, clippings and printed matter, correspondence, memoranda, paper, and report, relating to issues about censorship and textbook censorship
- "A Brief History of Teacher Professionalism," White House Conference on Preparing Tomorrow's Teachers, 2002 March 5 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  Includes related materials
- Review of The Revisionists Revised: Studies in the Historiography of American Education, 1977 (Box-folder 10: 2)
- Commencement address, Ramapo College, New Jersey, 1990 June 1 (Box-folder 10: 3)
- Clippings and textbook clips, 1952-1998 (Box-folder 10: 4-7)
- Creative Evolution, II and III, 1969-1981 (Box-folder 10: 8-10)
- Herbartianism, 1955-1967 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  Photocopies of articles
- Writings by others (Box-folder 11: 2)
- Hakim, Joy, 1987-1989. Includes her writings and correspondence, 1965-1986 (Box-folder 11: 3)
- Andy Hartman, 1991 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  Memoranda, notes for meeting with National Academy of Sciences, and materials relating to America 2000 Communities Special Assistance Program
- How Schools Shortchange Girls, American Association of University Women (AAUW) Report, 1992 (Box-folder 11: 5)
- The SAT Gender Gap: Identifying the Causes, report by Phyllis Rosser, Center for Women Policy Studies, 1989 (Box-folder 11: 6)
- Multiculturalism - J. Jorge Klor de Alva, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 11: 7-8)
  Correspondence and memoranda
- History (Box-folder 12:)
- General, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, newsletter, notes, program, and report
- Teaching, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 12: 2)
  Article and clippings
- Notes, undated (Box-folder 12: 3)
- World, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  A book by Jean Fritz and conference report
- Studies, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 12: 5)
  Clippings, printed matter, and speech by Robert R. Spillane
- School, undated (Box-folder 12: 6)
  Clippings
- Comments, 1985-1995 and undated (Box-folder 12: 7)
  Article, clippings, question paper, and speech
- Hillard, Asa G., 1978 (Box-folder 12: 8)
  Resource outline
- McMurray, Charles A., undated (Box-folder 12: 9)
  Book review and photocopy of a book
- Hirsch, E. D., Jr., 1987-1990 (Box-folder 12: 10)
  Articles
- Civil rights, 1977-1994 and undated (Box-folder 13: 1)
  Articles by James E. Colman and printed matter
- Coolidge, Calvin, 1968 and undated (Box-folder 13: 2)
  Introduction and note
- Bishop, John H., 1986-1995 and undated (Box-folder 13: 3-4)
  Articles, report, and working papers
- Humanities, 1979-1984 and undated (Box-folder 13: 5)
  Articles, bulletin, letter to the President from William J. Bennett, printed matter, and report
- Kearns, David, 1992 (Box-folder 13: 6)
- Knowledge (Box-folder 13:)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D. - On Dewey, 1952-1958 (Box-folder 13: 7)
    Photocopies of clippings
  - Items and literature, 1939-1994 (Box-folder 13: 8)
    Letters, printed matter, and speech
  - Exemplars, 1995 (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - Miscellany, 1995 and undated (Box-folder 13: 10)
- England, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  Briefing, clippings, curriculum vitae, letters, map, schedule, and related materials
- Evans, Ronald W., 1989 (Box-folder 14: 2)
  Article by Diane Ravitch and also about her. Includes writings by others
- Executive Commission - Papers presented to the National Commission on Excellence in Education, 1982-1983 and undated (Box-folder 14: 3)
- The English Journal, 1912-1914 (Box-folder 14: 4)
- Encyclopedia Britannica, 1980-1994 (Box-folder 14: 5)
  Correspondence, curriculum vitae, list of William Benton Foundation Board of Directors, memoranda, printed matter, and report
- Democracy Reader - Copyrights, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 14: 6)
  Correspondence, notes, permission to reprint copyrighted materials, table of contents, and updated list of permission and fees
- Democracy, 1991 and undated (Box-folder 14: 7)
  The Fundamentals of Democracy, article by Diane Ravitch and a cover letter
- Classics, 1987-1995 and undated (Box-folder 14: 8)
  Articles, clippings, letter, and newsletters
- Expanding environments, 1986 (Box-folder 15: 1)
  "The Erosion of History in American Schools, with Especial Attention to the Elementary School Curriculum," prepared for delivery at the 1986 Annual Meeting of the Organization of American Historians and the National Council on Public History. Includes a letter and notes
- Experimental Schools Projects, 1970-1983 (Box-folder 15: 2)
  Articles, letter, and printed matter
- National Commission on Excellence in Education, 1982-1983 and undated (Box-folder 15: 3-6)
  Papers and reports
- Gender, 1992-1996 and undated (Box-folder 16: 1-3)
  Draft article,clippings, correspondence, memoranda, news release, petition, remarks, and report
- Education statistics, 1991-1993 and undated (Box-folder 16: 4)
  Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, newsletter, printed matter, and related materials
- Ferry Margaret Grove, 1985 (Box-folder 16: 5)
  Dissertation, Arizona State University
- Free schools, 1972-1977 and undated (Box-folder 16: 6)
  Articles, list, and printed matter
- New York State, 1983-1995 and undated (Box-folder 17: 1-3)
  Booklet, budget, clippings, list of local assistant cuts, news release, printed matter, and related materials
- Office of Educational Research and Improvement (OERI)
  - General, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 17: 4)
    Correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, newsletter, and printed matter
  - Battles, 1992 (Box-folder 17: 5)
  - Budget, 1991-1993 and undated (Box-folder 17: 6-7)
    Correspondence, financial data, memoranda, newsletters, notes, tables, and related materials
  - Legislation, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 17: 8)
  - Publications, 1994 (Box-folder 17: 9)
    Newsletter
  - Technology, 1992 (Box-folder 17: 10)
    Memoranda
- National Assessment of Educational Progress (NAEP)
  - General, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    Chart, correspondence, paper, and printed matter
  - School level achievement, 1991-1992 and undated (Box-folder 18: 2)
    Correspondence, memoranda, and paper
  - Albert Shanker, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 18: 3)
    Clipping, memoranda, note, and press release
  - Literacy, 1988-1992 and undated (Box-folder 18: 4)
    Memoranda, statement by Diane Ravitch and related materials
- Brookings Institution, 2000 (Box-folder 18: 5)
  Report
- National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) (Box-folder 18:)
  - Form letter, 1987 (Box-folder 18: 6)
  - Sheldon Hackney's remarks and comments by Diane Ravitch and list of participants in scholars meeting, Chicago, Illinois, 1993-1994 and undated (Box-folder 18: 7)
  - Financial records, 1979-1988 (Box-folder 18: 8)
    Correspondence, financial status report, invoice, and statement of income policy
  - NEH, 1987 and undated (Box-folder 18: 9)
    Correspondence, financial records, memoranda, newsletter, note, payment orders, printed matter, and project description report
- Educational Excellence Network (EEN), 1985-1986 and undated (Box-folder 18: 10)
  Affirmative Action recruitment summary, budget, correspondence, list of grants and contributors, memoranda, notice of contracts, proposal, and status of grants
- New York State - Social studies, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 18: 11-13)
  Clippings, memoranda, and report
- Organization of American History (OAH), 1989 (Box-folder 18: 14)
  Letters
- Erich Martel, 1990 and undated (Box-folder 19: 1)
  Letter to Diane Ravitch and to the editor and paper by John Henrik Clarke
- Multiculturalism, 1984-1994 and undated (Box-folder 19: 2-4)
  Correspondence, letter to the editor, memoranda, newsletter, paper, printed matter, remarks, and speech. Includes a speech by Diane Ravitch at the Manhattan Institute on "Multiculturalism in the Curriculum"
- National Assessment of Educational Progress (NAEP), 1985-1986 and undated (Box-folder 19: 5)
  Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, news release, remarks, and related materials
- National Assessment of Educational Progress - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), 1983-1990 (Box-folder 19: 6-7)
  Chart, correspondence, curriculum vitae, printed matter, report, and related materials
- Spencer Foundation, 1980-1987 and undated (Box-folder 20: 1)
  Annual report, budget, correspondence, curriculum vitae, and list of grants
- Maryland State Department of Education - Standards, 1995 (Box-folder 20: 2)
- McMurray, Charles, 1982 (Box-folder 20: 3)
  Dissertation
- Mckinney Independent School District, 1992 and undated (Box-folder 20: 4-5)
  Correspondence, memoranda, note, printed matter, project description, talking points, and related materials
- Right wing, 1992-1993 undated (Box-folder 21: 1)
  Brochure, clipping, correspondence, guide to public schools, journal, printed matter, and related materials
- Standards
  - Report cards, 1985-1992 and undated (Box-folder 21: 2-3)
    Correspondence, newsletter, reports, and school profile
  - Mirrel, Jerry, and David Angus, 1994 (Box-folder 21: 4)
  - Porter, Andrew C., 1993 and undated (Box-folder 21: 5)
    Report on National Standards and School Improvement. Also includes Annual Report on Wisconsin Performance Assessment Development Project
  - Opportunity to Learn, 1994 (Box-folder 21: 6)
    Paper by Andrew Porter on guaranteeing good instruction
  - Kentucky, 1991-1992 and undated (Box-folder 21: 7)
    Annual report, clippings and printed matter, and performance level guides
  - National Council of Teachers of Mathematics (NCTM), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 21: 8)
  - Critics, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 21: 9)
    Clippings and newsletter
  - Framework, 1993 (Box-folder 21: 10)
  - Delaware, 1994 (Box-folder 21: 11)
    Newspapers
- Outcome Based Education (OBE), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 22: 1)
  Bulletin, chapter of a book by Judith Witmer, and newsletter
- Koretz, Daniel, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 22: 2)
  Includes papers by others
- Sizer, Tod, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 22: 3)
- Sources of Materials and Research about Teaching and Learning for Improving Nationwide Education (SMARTLINE), 1992 (Box-folder 22: 4)
  Memoranda and report
- Smith, Marshall S., 1990-1993 (Box-folder 22: 5)
- Socialization, 1995 (Box-folder 22: 6)
- Sobol, Thomas, 1991 (Box-folder 22: 7)
  Clippings, correspondence, and report
- Social Studies - Virginia, 1995 (Box-folder 22: 8)
  Correspondence and reports
- Speech materials, 1991-1992 and undated (Box-folder 22: 9)
  Clippings, memoranda, and printed matter
- Spending - Achievement, 1991-1994 and undated (Box-folder 22: 10)
  Correspondence, note, paper, and report
- Southern Regional Education Board (SREB), 1987-1988 (Box-folder 22: 11)
  Reports
- Teacher education, 1951-1986 and undated (Box-folder 23: 1)
  Photocopies of articles and notes
- Teacher education and social study elementary curriculum, 1988 (Box-folder 23: 2)
  Paper and a note
- Teachers College - Budget status and program detail activity, 1993 (Box-folder 23: 3)
- Technology, 1991-1993 and undated (Box-folder 23: 4)
  Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, proceedings of the Senate subcommittee, and report
- Tenure, undated (Box-folder 23: 5)
- Testing - Equity, 1993 (Box-folder 23: 6)
- General Standards, 1983-1993 (Box-folder 23: 7-8)
  Articles, brochure, clippings, correspondence, journal, newsletter, performance summary, report, and research study
- Science Standards, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 23: 9-10)
  Articles, clippings, correspondence, memoranda, newsletter, press release, proposal, report, and working paper
- General, 1989-1994 and undated (Box-folder 24: 1)
  Clippings, notes, research report, and projects
- Tracking, 1984-1992 and undated (Box-folder 24: 2)
  Bulletin, correspondence, chapter of a book, memoranda, press release, and report
- Civics, 1992 (Box-folder 24: 3)
  Agenda of a press conference, correspondence, and project report
- English, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 24: 4)
  Clippings, correspondence, and proposal
- Standards - Local, state, and regional, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 24: 5)
  Memoranda, status report, summary report, and Maryland school performance report
- History, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 24: 6)
  Articles, newsletter, and project update
- Articles by others, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 24: 7)
- Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development (ASCD), 1991 (Box-folder 24: 8)
  Standards for curriculum and instruction
- Arts, 1992 and undated (Box-folder 24: 9)
  Clippings and note
- Mathematics, 1968-1993 and undated (Box-folder 24: 10-11)
  Articles, brochure, catalog of educational materials, correspondence, newsletters, quarterly journal, and working papers
- Delivery, 1992-1994 and undated (Box-folder 25: 1-2)
  Charts, clippings, correspondence, newsletter, report, and related materials
- Transcripts - High Schools, 1984 and undated (Box-folder 25: 3)
- Course taking, 1984-1993 and undated (Box-folder 25: 4)